Guide to the Kirsten Delegard Thesis Research Notes, 1989 - 1990
Kirsten Delegard Thesis Research Notes1989 - 1990
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Kirsten Delegard
1000-69
2.0
7
Kirsten Delegard, a member of the class of 1990, wrote her senior thesis for the CSS major on the experience of women Wesleyan graduates from the beginning of the second period of coeducation in 1968 onward. During her time at Wesleyan, she was one of only five women in her CSS class, and her experiences prompted her to write the history. She presently works as a public historian. After receiving her Masters and PhD from Duke University, she published the book "Battling Miss Bolsheviki: The Origins of Female Conservatism in the United States." She is a Scholar-in-Residence at Augsburg College.
The Kristin Delegard Research Notes collection consists of over 800 completed surveys received from women graduates from the classes of 1970-79, 1984, and 1990 and the computer printouts of data. The surveys were sent to about 2,000 women, and questions related to the respondents biographies and experiences relating to gender, sexism, feminism, and other issues during these women's time before, at, and after Wesleyan.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No retrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Gift of Kirsten Delegard.
Biographical Note
A College of Social Studies major in the class of 1990, Kirsten Delegard was one of only 5 women in her CSS class. As she notes in her thesis, and as many have noted before and since, CSS is a notoriously male-dominated major in terms of both student population and core theorists-though there are arguments to be made about the increasingly equal distribution of its professorship. As she writes in the introduction to her thesis, her experience as part of a marginal group influenced her decision to write a thesis about the experiences of women throughout the second period of coeducation at Wesleyan, which began in 1968. She wrote that she "felt inhibited, discouraged, and frustrated as a woman in a program pervaded by both blatant and subtle sexism." She offers several anecdotes that illustrate this experience.
"In classes and department social events professors and undergraduates used sexist language and humor that patronized, demeaned, and objectified women students. In classes where aggressive debate characterized discussion, women were more often interrupted, ridiculed for their comments, and ignored by male undergraduates and professors. While I succeeded academically, my confidence in my abilities was undermined by sexist comments. One professor told me, 'I think you did not do well in my class because women think differently, women can't understand power,' while another said he was surprised to find a woman excelling."
Because of her experience, she felt compelled to examine how women at Wesleyan have dealt at various periods with being a traditionally marginalized group. Based primarily on the results to the surveys, which are included in the collection and described in detail below, Delegard wrote her senior thesis for CSS, titled "Mixed Memories: Reflections On Twenty-Two Years of Coeducation at Wesleyan."
Since graduating from Wesleyan, Delegard received her Masters and PhD in history from Duke University. She currently works as a public historian in her hometown of Minneapolis, Minnesota, and is noted for creating the Historyapolis Project, which is meant to "make the history of [Minneapolis] accessible," given what Delegard sees as the city's blindness to its tumultuous past and its discomfort with confronting it. The project "seeks to produce a new book-length history of the city," and to "catalyze community dialogue around some of the most challenging aspects of local history."
In 2012, Delegard published her first full-length work-Battling Miss Bolsheviki: The Origins of Female Conservatism in the United States. In the book, Delegard explores why once-respected female reformers lost authority after women won the right to vote, and argues that female conservatives pushed out these reformers with anti-radical agendas. Delegard has also been involved in the writing and editing of several other academic texts, and at time of writing is working on a new history of Minneapolis under the Historyapolis project.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of over 800 surveys received from individual women graduates as well as computer printouts of data gained from these surveys.
Most of the surveys are labeled with a number on the upper right-hand side. Surveys 1-821 are labeled, with the possible exception of numbers 15, 65, 185, 441, 459, 509, and 591, which are missing. 23 surveys are unlabelled, or perhaps have lost their labels over time. The surveys are stored in order of numbered label, with the unlabelled surveys stored in a separate folder.
Delegard sent the surveys to approximately 2,000 graduates from the classes of 1970-79, 1984, and 1990. The surveys ask a series of biographical questions such as year of graduation at Wesleyan, parents' education level and occupation, and personal marital status. The surveys also ask a variety of questions about the graduates' decision to attend Wesleyan and their experiences while at Wesleyan, particularly with gender, sexism, and feminism. Though many of the women wrote in brief answers, others provided lengthy responses. Delegard quoted extensively from the written answers and used the multiple choice or short answers for substantial statistical analysis.
Included in the collection are the computer printouts from Delegard's statistical analysis of the surveys. Comprising three boxes, the printouts show the extent of Delegard's data exploration of the surveys she received, and provide an excellent example of early 1990s computer processing and research techniques.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Delegard, Kirsten.; Women college students.; Women--Education (Higher).; Coeducation.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.
Related Material
Delegard, Kirsten, Mixed memories: reflections on twenty-two years of coeducation at Wesleyan, honors thesis, 1990.
Coeducation at Wesleyan Collection, ca. 1867-1912
Knight, Louise Wilby Papers, 1971-1972
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Kirsten Delegard Thesis Research Notes, 1989-1990, 4 Hollinger boxes, 3 oversize boxes
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 1-40 (missing 15), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 41-80 (missing 65), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 81-122, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 123-169, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 170-206 (missing 185), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 207-245, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 246-295, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 296-339, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 340-376, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 377-418, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 419-450 (missing 441), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 451-487 (missing 459), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 488-520 (missing 509), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 521-562, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 563-603 (missing 591), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 604-644, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 645-685, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 686-726, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 727-777, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys 778-821, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Wesleyan female graduate surveys, unlabeled, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Computer printouts, 1989-1990 (Box 5-7)